<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here is the swearers and they who swear falsly, and likewise they who compel men to swear, all tried by the law of the spirit of life which is in Chirst Jesus. Which law is holy, just, pure, and good; and all of them found guilty of sin and transgression against the true and living God; and also sentence pronounced against them all, that so transgress the Law of God, who with the wicked, and all they who forget God, must be turned into Hell, except they repent speedily; for with God there is no respect of persons in Judgement. Written the 21. day of the third month, 1661. by me Henry Clark.</title>
            <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4454A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231477</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897035</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897035</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137042</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79863)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2459:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here is the swearers and they who swear falsly, and likewise they who compel men to swear, all tried by the law of the spirit of life which is in Chirst Jesus. Which law is holy, just, pure, and good; and all of them found guilty of sin and transgression against the true and living God; and also sentence pronounced against them all, that so transgress the Law of God, who with the wicked, and all they who forget God, must be turned into Hell, except they repent speedily; for with God there is no respect of persons in Judgement. Written the 21. day of the third month, 1661. by me Henry Clark.</title>
                  <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Swearing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137042:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HERE IS THE SWEARERS, AND They who ſwear falſly, and likewiſe they who compel men to ſwear, all tried by the Law of the Spirit of life WHICH IS IN CHRIST JESUS.</p>
            <p>Which LAW is holy, juſt, pure, and good; and all of them found guilty of ſin and tranſgreſſion againſt the true and living God; and alſo Sentence pronounced againſt them all, that ſo tranſgreſs the Law of God, who with the wicked, and all they who forget God, muſt be turned into Hell, except they repent ſpeedily; for with God there is no reſpect of perſons in Judgement.</p>
            <q>By ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and committing adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, they break out, and blood toucheth blood; Therefore ſhall the Land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein ſhall languiſh, with the Beaſts of the field, and with the fowls of the Heaven; yea, the Fiſhes of the Sea alſo ſhall be taken away, <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea 4.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Written the 21. day of the third Month, 1661. by me <hi>HENRY CLARK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, in the year 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:137042:2"/>
            <head>Here is the Swearers, and they who Swear falſly, and likewiſe they who Compel men to Swear, all tried by the Law of the Spirit of Life, which is in Chriſt Jeſus; which Law is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, juſt, pure and good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the time of Ignorance and Darkneſs God winked at, and paſſed by many things whereby mankind did tranſgreſs the pure and righteous Law of God, which is holy, juſt, and good; but now Light is come into the world, even that Light which has been hid from the wiſe and prudent of ages and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations paſt: the which Light God who (is rich in mercy and love through the abundance thereof) commanded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined into the hearts of Babes and Sucklings, and they who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the region and the ſhadow of Death ſaw this great Light, which hath given unto them the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Light, the true Light by which all things that are reproved are made manifeſt. Therefore now God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all men every where to repent, and to turn from Darkneſs unto the Light, and from the power of Sathan unto God who is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all. Now the Light ſhineth, all men every where will be left without excuſe: Therefore turn ye, turn ye every one from the evil of your ways, and come to the knowledge of the Truth, as God would have you, that your ſouls may be ſaved: For to fear God, and keep his Commandements, is the whole duty of man: and the fear of the Lord is to depart from iniquity. Therefore <hi>let every one that nameth the Name of</hi> JESUS <hi>depart from iniquity:</hi> For becauſe of Swearing and Forſwearing, and Swearing falſly; Lying, Killing, Stealing, and committing of Adultery, the Land mourneth: and as for the Rulers their violence is evil, and their force is not right towards the People: But the true and living God he hears the Cry of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and ſees and beholds their Oppreſſors; yea he doth hear the Cry of his Elect, that cries unto him day and night, and he will avenge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137042:2"/>them of their Oppreſſors ſpeedily. And know ye this ye Kings and Rulers of the Earth, that with God there is no reſpect of perſons in judgment; and to judgment ye muſt all come, to give an account to the King of Kings, the great Judge of all the Earth, of all your works and deeds that have been done in and by your bodies: And ſeeing it is thus written, that ſurely men of low degree are vanity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.9.</note> and men of high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree are a lie; to be laid in the ballance they are altogether lighter then vanity. Then how will ye be able to ſtand before the true and living God, who is a conſuming fire, or what anſwer can ye make him unto this one queſtion when he comes to plead with you: What do ye cauſe and compell the people to Swear and tranſgreſs my Law, and do ye not puniſh ſuch as fear my Name, and refuſe to Swear, in obedience to my Command, ſaith the Lord God, &amp;c. who hath required this thing at your hands: to what will you flee for excuſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Law of the land it cannot excuſe you: Why? Becauſe that Acts of Parliaments, are acts of mens wills, and not the Oracles of God: and Parliaments as well as Councils may be led by wrong principles, <hi>[being not guided by the Spirit of God]</hi> and ſo erre, and make Laws of vanity; or Acts of Errours, and Statutes that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and not good, becauſe they contradict the Law of God, Therefore they cannot juſtifie your actions.</item>
               <item>2. Neither will the Antiquity of your Law for ſwearing, excuſe nor juſtifie you any more, then the Temple at Jeruſalem which was ſtanding many Generations before <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> daies, could juſtifie the Jews in their Murder, Adultery, and falſe ſwearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither will it free you from the guiltineſs of ſin in the ſight of God, any more then <hi>Abraham</hi> could free the Jews from the bondage of ſin: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they pleaded, ſaying, <hi>They had Abraham for their Father,</hi> yet Chriſt told them, <hi>Whoſoever committeth ſin, is ſervant to ſin, and ſo not free but in bondage,</hi> as ye are to your wills and luſts, for which ye plead a Law. But it is a Maxime in your own Law, <hi>That what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in its Original is altogether illegal and unjuſt, can never by tract or length of time, or by any Act or Acts ſubſequent, be they what they will, in any kinde or conſtruction of Law, be made juſt or legal,</hi> &amp;c. And the Judges of this land know this Maxime to be true: Therefore the more inexcuſable are the Rulers and Judges of this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they ſet at nought, and reject the Counſel and Spirit of the true and living God, which ſhould be their Rule and guide to make all their Laws by: and if Laws, Acts, and Statutes, be not made according to that Rule, they can never be legal, juſt, nor good.</item>
               <item>3. Neither can the example of other Nations herein excuſe, or juſtifie you: Why? becauſe that the Cuſtoms, Statutes, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Nations, are vanity, and the works of Errour, and not of God: for the waies of the wicked are abomination to the Lord, <hi>Therefore ye should not follow a multitude to do evil,</hi> nor learn the wayes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137042:3"/>of the Heathen, who are Idolaters, but refrain your feet from their paths, and follow the true and living God fully: and as for thoſe who go under the denomination of Chriſtian Princes and Kings, or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, I do not hear of any one of them that feareth God, and worketh righteouſneſs: and I do believe there is not ſcarce one of them that does, and my reaſon is, Becauſe they uſe ſuch acts of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and cruelty towards thoſe that fear God and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: for if they themſelves feared God, they would depart from iniquity, and leave off their acts of violence, cruelty and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſuch as fear God and keep his Commandements, or if they loved God, then they would keep his Commandments, and be a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to all evil doers, and love them that are begotten to the Truth of God, the which they do not: But as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid, <hi>I know the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of them that ſay they are Iews &amp; are not, but are the Synagogue of Satan:</hi> So I ſay, I know the blaſphemy of them that lye, and ſay they are Chriſtians, but are not; but are members of the great whore of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> for I know what the tree is by its fruits; Therefore O King and Rulers of <hi>England,</hi> leave the paths of the wicked, and go not in the way of evili men: avoid it: paſs by it: turn from it, and paſs away; for they ſleep not except they have done miſchief: and their ſleep is taken away, unleſs they cauſe ſome to fall: for they eat the bread of wickedneſs, and drink the wine of violence; Therefore their wayes and cuſtomes are evil and vain, and not to be followed. Therefore take warning, and while ye have time, priſe it, except ye intend to go on in wickedneſs, and ſo to partake of all the plagues that is a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon all the Kings, Rulers, and Judges of the earth, who are drunk with the bloud of the Saints, and holy Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Come now all you who command and compel men to ſwear By forms of Oathes; and likewiſe all you who ſwear by forms of Oathes, or otherwayes; for the end of my writing is for the convincing of you all, that ſwearing, and compelling to ſwear, is a ſinne againſt the true and living God: and that you may all ſee that by the law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, you are all evil doers, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours of a pure, holy, and a juſt law; <hi>For God ſo loved the world, That he gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth on him should not perish, but have everlaſting life:</hi> he was in the beginning before <hi>Abraham,</hi> and a greater then <hi>Abraham</hi> was, is he: of whom <hi>Moſes,</hi> a ſervant of God wrote, ſaying, <hi>The Lord God ſaid, I will raiſe them up a Prophet from among their brethren, like unto thee; and I will put my words in his mouth, and he shall ſpeak whatſoever I command him, and whoſoever will not hearken unto my words, which he shall speak in my name, I will require it of him:</hi> and ſaid <hi>Peter, Every ſoul which will not hear that Prophet, shall he deſtroyed from among the people.</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt being come, he taught his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>But I ſay unto you ſwear not at all;</hi> for God who at ſundry times, and in divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſpake in times paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137042:3"/>laſt dayes ſpoken unto us by his Son, [who is the end of the Law and the Prophets, to every one that believeth in him: and he ſpake and ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>] He whom God hath appointed heir of all things, by whom alſo he made the world, who being the brightneſs of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the expreſs image of his perſon, and is ſate down on the right hand of his Majeſty on high, being made much better then the Angels, as he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name then they; for all the Angels muſt worſhip him, and to the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue ſhall confeſs (by the Spirit of God) that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of God the Father: and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> further ſaid, That at that time when Ieſus took <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> his Brother, up into a high Mountain apart, behold a bright cloud overſhadowed them, and a voice was heard out of the cloud, and this voice which came from heaven, we heard, ſaid <hi>Peter,</hi> when we were with him in the Mount; which voice ſaid, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed, hear ye him.</hi> He is the end of the Law and the Prophets to every one that believeth in him. And Jeſus Chriſt taught his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>But I ſay unto you ſwear not at all,</hi> &amp;c. And which of you all is it, that will forſake to go with a Kings Son, that is far more excellent then the ſervant of that King, to follow that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, the which if you ſhould, would not the King be much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with you: Conſider of it: Moſes was a ſervant of God, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the houſe of God, and did all things according to the pattern ſhewd of God in the Mount: but when Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of the living God, who had the more excellent name was come from his Father, then all that received him and believed on his Name, forſook <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Law, and followed him, and obeyed him who was the end of the Law and the Prophets, to every one that believeth in him, Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God, who ſaid unto them, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Now I ſay there is a Law that came by Moſes, which was given unto him in Mount Sinai, for the children of Iſrael onely (and not to any other people or Nation) to obſerve and keep [but grace and Truth, which was, and is preached to all Nations, came by Jeſus Chriſt] For God had choſen them, <hi>viz</hi> the children of Iſrael above all other people that were upon the face of the earth, to be a peculiar people unto himſelf; and unto them were committed the Oracles or Counſels of God: <hi>For he shewed his word unto Iacob, and his Statutes, and his Iudgements unto Iſrael:</hi> and ſaid David, <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation, for his judgements they have not known:</hi> and it is written in Moſes Law, <hi>Hear, O Iſrael, thou shalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and shalt ſwear by his name, and not by the falſe gods that other nations ſwear by: and an Oath of confirmation, was to them an end of all ſtrife:</hi> and that was thus, if any man deliver unto his neighbour an Aſſe, or an Ox, or a Sheep, or any beaſt to keep, and it dye, or be hurt, or driven away no man ſeeing it, then ſhall an Oath of the Lord
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137042:4"/>(and not Oaths of mens making up into a form) be between them both, that he who received the cattle to keep, hath not put his hand unto his neighbours goods, to hurt, kill or drive them away, and the owner of the goods was to accept of the Oath of God, that the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had ſworn, and the receiver of the goods to keep, was not to make them good: and this oath of God taken before a Iudge, was to them an end of all ſtrife: but other Nations were not required to ſweat by that Oath of God, for as Paul ſaid, <hi>That God in times paſt ſuffered all Nations to walk in their own ways</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But when Chriſt Jeſus the Son of the living God came in the fleſh, he came to condemn ſin in the fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 14, 15, 16.</note> and to deſtroy the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, which was the cauſe of ſtrife, that ſo the effect, <hi>viz. Oaths,</hi> might ceaſe; for he is the end of the Law and the Prophets to all that believe in his Name; and to as many as received him, and believed on his Name, he gave them power to become the ſons of God, and as many as are the ſons of God, are led by the Spirit of God into all truth, out of ſtrife, ſin and iniquity, which was the Occaſion of an Oath of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, which was to put an end to all ſtrife between man and man, according to the Law that came by <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of God, for the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely to obſerve and keep: But the Word which God put into the mouth of his onely begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt, to ſpeak and declare, was to be preached to all Nations every where, that men might turn from vanity, and leave off ſin and iniquity that cauſed ſtrife between man and man, to ſerve the: true &amp; living God: For when Chriſt Jeſus ſent forth his Apoſtles, he commanded them to go and teach all Nations, ſaying, <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel in every creature, and teach all Nations to obſerve all things whatſoever that I have commanded you:</hi> Now Chriſt Jeſus taught them, his Apoſtles and Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>But I ſay unto you, Swear not at all:</hi> here is the command of Chriſt, the words which God put in his mouth, according to <hi>Moſes</hi> writing, <hi>I will put my words into his mouth, and he ſhall ſpeak unto them in my Name all that I shall command him,</hi> who ſaid unto them, <hi>Swear not at all, neither by Heaven, for it is God's throne:</hi> And ſaid Chriſt to the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Wo unto you, ye blind Guides:</hi> He that ſwears by Heaven, ſweareth by the throne of God, and him that ſitteth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Heaven is Gods throne, and God ſitteth on his throne, and he that ſweareth by the Heaven, ſweareth by God that ſitteth thereon; the which ſwearing Chriſt doth forbid, although according to the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> it was lawful for them to ſwear by his Name, [<hi>Jehovah</hi> is his Name] before Chriſt came, who is the end of the Law and the Prophets to all that believe in his Name, who is the Son of God, who ſaid, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſwear by the Earth, for it is his foot-ſtool:</hi> Is the Earth God's Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool? then he that ſweareth by the Earth, ſweareth by God that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his foot thereon, according to what Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He that ſweareth by the Heaven, ſweareth by the Throne of God, and by God who ſitteth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and ſaid Chriſt, <hi>Neither ſwear by Ieruſalem, for it is the City of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137042:4"/>great King:</hi> Who is he? the true and living God, the King of Kings: He that ſweareth by the City of the great King, ſweareth by the King himſelf: For ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Whoſo ſhall ſwear by the Temple, ſweareth by it, and him that dwelleth therein:</hi> And doth not God dwell in his temple? then he that ſweareth by the temple where God dwelleth, ſweareth by God that dwelleth therein, according to Chriſt's words, who ſpake the truth, and as he meant. So then my Argument is ſtill, that he that ſweareth by the Bible, ſweareth not by it alone, but likewiſe by all things that is written in every part of it at once. And again Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Neither shalt thou ſwear by thy head, becauſe thou canſt not make one hair white or black:</hi> Now I ſay, it is God that made every man's head, and the hairs thereof, white or black; therefore he that ſweareth by his Head, ſweareth by God who made his Head, and the Hairs thereof,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3</note> white or black: And furthermore it is written, that the Head of every man is Chriſt, and ought not man to be ſubject to his Head, Law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Judge, Chriſt Jeſus the good Shepherd, Biſhop, and Saviour of his ſoul? Now all ye that ſwear, and compel men to ſwear, judge ye by the Law and Teſtimony of the ſpirit of Life which is in Chriſt Jeſus, whether it be good and lawful for ye thus to do, yea or nay; read it, and try whether the Law of the Spirit of Life which is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, will juſtiſie you in ſwearing, or compelling men to ſwear, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you eternally for your ſo doing: For this ye ſhall all know, that he that believeth not in the onely begotten Son of God, is condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed already, becauſe he hath not believed in the Name of the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son of God, who is come a light to enlighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18.</note> and the glory of the people Iſrael. Therefore</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider all you that forget God: for although the Jews ſwore by the name of the true and living God, according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law: and the Heathens, Pagans, Infidels, or Idolaters, who God in time paſt and now ſuffereth to walk in their own ways, did, and do ſwear by their dead Idols, or falſe gods, which was and is the workmanſhip of their own hands: yet this muſt not be a precedent, or an example for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to Swear at all, by any Oath, or form of Oath whatſoever: for God hath called all the true Chriſtians who believe on the Name of his onely begoten Son, from amongſt the Jews, Heathens, Pagans, Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, &amp;c. and hath ſeparated them from them and their Laws and Cuſtoms to follow his Son Jeſus Chriſt the Captain of their Salvation, and to worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth, and to walk before him in fear, &amp; in holineſs &amp; righteouſneſs all the days of their lives: Therefore it is not lawful for Chriſtians to ſwear by their head &amp; Captain of their Salvation, who teaches them <hi>not to Swear at all:</hi> And as it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for Chriſtians to Swear, neither is it becoming, nor doth become any true Chriſtian to Swear by any form of Oath that is of any mans making whatſoever: For he that ſweareth by any Oath whatſoever that is of man's or mens inventing, contriving and drawing up into a form, it is all one as if he ſwore by an Idol, which proceeds from the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137042:5"/>invention of mens brains, the imagination of their hearts, and the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of their own hands: For the one is as much out of, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Truth as it is in Jeſus Chriſt, as the other is: and therefore fore they are to be denied of all the true Chriſtians: Why? Becauſe that as the Idols or falſe gods are onely the invention of mens brains, the imagination of their hearts, and alſo the workmanſhip of their hands. Therefore they are lies, vanity, and the work of Error: So likewiſe all forms of Oaths which are ſet forth to publike view in theſe days for men to ſwear by, are onely inventions of mens brains, the imaginations of their wicked and deceitful hearts, and the workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of their own hands, and not the Oath of God: therefore they are lyes, vanity, and the works of error, and not the work of God; for the works of God are true; but it is written, <hi>Surely</hi> (ſaid <hi>David</hi>) <hi>Men of low degree are vanity, and men of high degree are a lye;</hi> therefore whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is that ſuch men act or contrive by the invention of their own brains,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 62.9.</note> and the imaginations of their own hearts in imitation of the works of God, or the ways of his worſhip, is not true, but are meer lyes, vanities, falſhood, and the work of errors; which acts, works, and forms of Oaths are not to be ſubjected to, but are to be rejected by all true Chriſtians: Why?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe it is neither lawful nor comely for Chriſtians to ſwear an Oath, nor by any form of Oath or thing whatſoever; for Chriſtians, the Diſciples of Chriſt were taught, and have learned of their Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus, not to ſwéar at all: and what they were taught, and what they received of Chriſt, that they declared and taught to others in obedience to Chriſts command, who ſaid unto them, <hi>Go and teach all Nations, teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you,</hi> who commanded them not to ſwear at all: and it is upon record to be ſeen, that <hi>Iames</hi> an Apoſtle, a Diſciple of Ieſus Chriſt, and a true Chriſtian likewiſe, wrote to the Brethren (Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) of the twelve tribes, which were ſcattered abroad upon the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution that aroſe upon the Church which was at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſaying <hi>My brethren, but above all things ſwear not at all, neither by Heaven, neither by the Earth, neither by any other Oath, leaſt ye fall into condemnation &amp;c.</hi> Which words both <hi>Iames</hi> and the other Diſciples had learned of Chriſt Jeſus the good Shepherd and Biſhop of their ſouls, who went up into a Mountain, and when he was ſate, his Diſciples came unto him, and he opened his mouth, and taught them thus, with other Doctrine not to ſwear at all, which they obeyed and kept: And ſo likewiſe all others who believed on his Name through their preaching, did obſerve the ſame commands of Chriſt, and do them. For in the dayes of <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Domitian,</hi> both Heathen Emperors, and cruel tyrants, was very great and ſore perſecution of the Chriſtians, and they had a form of an oath for men to ſwear by; and the Inquiſitors of their Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion put the Chriſtians whom they perſecuted, to ſweare by their form of Oath, whether that they were Chriſtians, or no: but the Chriſtians reſuſed to ſwear, confeſſing and ſaying that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137042:5"/>they were Chriſtians, and could not deny Chriſt not his Doctrine: And then according to the Heathens Law, ſentence of death was pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the Chriſtians by the Proconſul, and forthwith the ſentence was put in execution by wicked, blood-thirſty men, who put the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to death, ſome after one manner, and ſome after another, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the wills of thoſe cruel tyrants the Emperors; and ſo I finde that the like Oath was required of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> by the Proconſul at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> which was in theſe words following thus: Polycarpus, <hi>thou shalt ſwear by the</hi> Emperors <hi>good fortune, and by the proſperity of</hi> Ceſar, <hi>and declare the truth, whether in very deed thou art a Chriſtian or no.</hi> But <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarpus</hi> refuſed to ſwear, or to deny Chriſt and his Doctrine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed himſelf to be a Chriſtian: So he was led away to be burned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the age of fourſcore and ſix years, or more. So likewiſe it is recorded, that the Chriſtian Martyrs in King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond's days, and in <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth's days, and in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> did bear a good teſtimony againſt Swearing, and likewiſe did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſwear, according to the command of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> Therefore I ſay, it is neither lawful nor comely for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to ſwear, for if they ſhould, it may be ſaid to them as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Iews</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Who art thou that teacheſt another should not ſwear, and doſt thou thy ſelf ſwear, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all thoſe who had, and have but the Name of Chriſtians onely, but lived not, nor do live in the life and power that the true Chriſtians lived, and do live in; or all they who had, and have got into a form of godlineſs, and denyed, and do deny the power thereof, which all they that were, and are truly godly lived, and do live in: I ſay, that even ſuch there were, and are, who ſought, and ſeek to the Powers of the Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> to the Kings and Rulers thereof for protection in their meer form of godlineſs onely, the which the true Chriſtians neither did, nor do ſuch things; for they knowing that the true and living God whom they ſerve is all-ſufficient by his power to keep and preſerve them out of the hands of all their Enemies, if he wil, and none can touch them; but if not, then they ſubmit to his wil in whatſoever he requires of them, although it be to the loſs of all things, or the laying down of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: But they who have got into, and live in a form of godlineſs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they cannot truſt God, without they have the help and aſſiſtance of the Kings and Rulers of the Earth to protect them by a Law of their making: And therefore the Kings and Rulers of the earth (for the more better ſecurity of thoſe ſeeming Formaliſts aſſiſtance to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a conformity to their wills and laws) they contrive and frame an Image, or an Oath or Oaths, for thoſe ſeeming Formaliſts to ſwear fealty to them by, juſt like the Heathens that ſwore by their falſe gods that were made with hands, fealty to their Emperors and Kings, even ſo do they, and all they that wil not ſwear by thoſe Oaths of their making, ſhall have no protection by them.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> formerly Queen of <hi>England,</hi> was (according to that knowledge ſhe had in thoſe dayes) more merciful then her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137042:6"/>were, for that there is a Law that was made in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th. year of her reign, that it ſhould not be lawful for any perſon or perſons to ſlay or kil any perſon or perſons, in any manner attainted, or hereafter to be attainted of, in, or upon any <hi>premunire, &amp;c.</hi> read the Law, cap. 1. And ſo they make good the words of Chriſt who ſaid, <hi>The world loves its own.</hi> And thus the wicked Heathens, Pagans, Infidels, outward For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſts, Hypocritical profeſſors of Chriſtianity; for like as their Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are, ſo are the people; for they all combine together againſt the Lord and his annointed, the true <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for ſaid <hi>David, The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed plotteth againſt the juſt, and gnasheth upon him with his teeth; the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then rage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37.12</note> 
               <hi>and the people imagine a vain thing; the Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, and Rulers take counſel together, ſaying, Come, let us break their Bonds aſſunder, let us caſt away their Cords from us:</hi> nay, they ſwear that they will puniſh and deſtroy them all, <hi>viz.</hi> the true Chriſtians, as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Schiſmaticks, Phanaticks, and Non-conformiſts to our Laws, &amp;c. and all the rude multitude of profane Drunkards and Swearers, at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very occaſion or word, murderers, ſighters, quarrellers, whores, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, adulterers, fornicators, thieves, robbers, idolators, image-makers, hypocrites, and outward formaliſts, will all run and go, and lay their hands upon a Bible, and ſwear by it, and the forms of oaths that they have made, and kiſs the Bible when they have done, that they will ſtand by, aid and aſſiſt the Kings, Rulers, Judges, Iuſtices, Mayors, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, Bailiffs, Conſtable, and others, in the doing of any act of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, cruelty, oppreſſion, yea even to death it ſelf, againſt the true Chriſtians who ſear the true and living God, and dare not run with them into the ſame exceſs of riot, revellings, banquettings, chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wantonneſs, drunkenneſs, laſciviouſneſs, and ſwearing, as the Kings, Rulers Ptieſts and people do run into; therefore they hate the true Chriſtians,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.13 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4.</note> and ſpeak all manner of evil of them, and ſeek to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them from off the face of the earth, that God may not have a temple to dwell in, nor the Son of God a place to lay his head in upon the earth, with ſuch as believe in his Name, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> &amp;c. So that here is no injunction laid upon, nor liberty allowed to the true Chriſtians to ſwear by any form of Oath, Allegiance to the Kings or Rulers of the Earth, or otherwayes, in whatſoever nature, manner, or thing be it to be ſworn unto, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore if he who <hi>shall break one of the leaſt of Gods commandments, and shall teach men ſo to do,</hi> ſaid Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>shall be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> then what ſhall all they be called or counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of, that not only break and tranſgreſs Gods commandments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but likewiſe compel others ſo to do? I ſay; certainly they are worthy to have the like puniſhment, plagues and torment, that <hi>Pharo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> had, and in the end to be drowned in the ſea; or there reward like as had that wicked <hi>Iehoram,</hi> who wrought evil in the eyes of the Lord himſelf, and cauſed the Inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to go a whoring like to the whoredoms of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and compel
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137042:6"/>
               <hi>Iudah</hi> thereunto, for the which wickedneſs, God ſmote the King <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam</hi> himſelf with a ſore and an incurable diſeaſe in his bowels,<note place="margin">Read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> ſo that his bowels fell out by reaſon of his ſickneſs: and moreover God ſtirred up the ſpirit of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and they came up into Iudah, and brake into it, and carried away all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that was in the Kings houſe, and his Sons alſo: and read and ſee what came upon <hi>Iudah</hi> in the days of <hi>Ioash,</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> [after the death of <hi>Iehoiada</hi>] and of <hi>Ioash</hi> himſelf for hearkening unto the Princes of <hi>Iudah</hi> that made obeyſance unto him, who then left the houſe of the Lord God, and ſerved Groves and Idols, and at the Kings commandment ſtoned to death <hi>Zechariah,</hi> the Son of <hi>Iehoiada</hi> between the Temple and the Altar, for the which the <hi>Syrians</hi> came with a ſmall company of men, and the Lord delivered a very great hoſt into their hands, and they deſtroyed all the Princes of the people, and ſent all the ſpoil of them to the King of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24. <hi>chap. Ier.</hi> 52. <hi>ch.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. and read what became upon <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and all the people of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> and upon <hi>Herod</hi> the King, who ſtretched out his hand againſt the true Chriſtians, that is the Church of Chriſt. Read <hi>Acts</hi> the 12. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further I ſay, that ſuch Kings, Rulers, and Iudges, or others who tranſgreſs the Laws of God themſelves, and compel others ſo to do, are even worthy of, and fit for the fire that burns, and is never quenched; and likewiſe for the worm that continually gnaws, and never dies, and for the pit and the ſnare; for <hi>Tophet</hi> is ordained of old, yea for the Kings it is prepared: he hath made it deep and large, the pile thereof is fire and much wood, and the breath of the Lord like a ſtream of Brimſtone, doth kindle it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30 33. And ſo worthy to be called fit companions for the Divel and his Angels, and not Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and thus ye may ſee what a fearfull thing it is for to fall into the hands of the true and living God, who is a conſuming fire to all the wicked, who with all they that forget God, muſt be turned into hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> conſider this, and learn to be wiſe ye Kings, Princes, Iudges, and Rulers of the earth, and be inſtructed to ſerve the Lord with fear, and let your rejoycing be with trembling before the living God: come &amp; bow down at the feet of Ieſus, and kiſs the Son leſt he be angry with you, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little: Therefore while you have time, priſe it; for why will ye dye? why will ye periſh from off the face of the earth, and be no more ſeen nor heard of. O ye Kings, Iudges, and Rulers of the earth, to day, to day, if ye expect mercy from the Lord, ceaſe from evil, and learn to do well, and believe on the Name of Ieſus Chriſt, that your ſouls may be ſaved, or elſe ye periſh eternally; for with God there is no reſpect of perſons in judgement, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, but tell him plainly of his faults: Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy neighbour, that thou bear not ſin for him: <hi>He that hath an ear, let him hear, and he that will be filthy, let him be filthy ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:137042:7"/>About the time of Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> the ſecond, [and before the year 590. for in that year the Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> dyed according to former wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters] there was a decree made, called <hi>the Canon of Matiſcon, for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring of Prieſts;</hi> in Latine it runs thus, <hi>Conſilium Matiſconenſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum,</hi> and thus it was decreed, Cap. 15. by the ſaid Council.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That if a lay-man ſhall meet in the way ſome better man of the Clergy, the lay-man ſhall in the loweſt manner of courteſie ſtoop re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently, and bow down to him.</item>
               <item>2. If the lay-man be on horſe back, and the Prieſt alſo, then the lay-man to put off his hood off his head, and do his duty of ſalutation.</item>
               <item>3. But if the Prieſt be on foot, and the lay-man on horſe back, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently he ſhall light from his horſe, and perform his due honour to the ſaid Clerk.</item>
               <item>4. Whatſoever he be that ſhall tranſgreſs theſe Canons, which be decreed by the inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, let him be ſuſpended out of the Church, which he will not honour in her Miniſters, even ſo long as ſhall pleaſe the Biſhop of that See, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for proof of this, read in a Book called, <hi>The defence of Prieſts marriages,</hi> Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Richard Iugge,</hi> Printer then to the <hi>Queen Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and dedicated to <hi>Philip</hi> &amp; <hi>Mary,</hi> who were the chief Rulers of the land.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But I finde in the Book of Martyrs, pages 496. and 500. and it was in <hi>Queen Mary's</hi> days, Anno 1555, that Doctor <hi>Nicholas Ridley</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to move or put off his Cap before the Court in honour of the Pope, or to the Cardinal the Popes Legate: For ſaid <hi>Brooks,</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter, Put off your cap Mr.</hi> Ridley, <hi>and put you on this Surplice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ridley</hi> ſaid, <hi>Not I truly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Said <hi>Brooks, But you muſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Ridley</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing it is thus written, that Chriſt Ieſus the Son of God ſaid to the Iews,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.44</note> 
               <hi>How can ye believe which receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour which cometh from God onely:</hi> ſo I ſay accordingly as <hi>Iames</hi> ſaid, <hi>That the faith of Ieſus Chriſt ſtandeth not in the reſpect of perſons: Therefore let all people judge according to the Law and the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that is bound up among the Diſciples,</hi> Whether that Decree, Canon, or Conſtitution made in the Council of <hi>Matiſcon</hi> for the honouring of Prieſts, Clerks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was made by the inſpiration of the Spirit of God, as they ſaid it was, yea, or nay? Or whether it came not from that proud ſpirit of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that was once in the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and which afterward got into the proud Pope, and the proud Prelate, and ſate in Counſel among them, inſpiring of them to make a Decree or Canon for the honouring of them and their adherents with Cap and Knee? Seeing that <hi>they had not the honour which comes from God onely:</hi> judge ye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
